-==www.RagBear.com==- 是, 首相  第2季第4集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=破烂熊字幕组=- 翻译: tanya312 校对&时间轴: tpring
利益冲突
早上好 首相
Good morning, Prime Minister.
您在看报纸吗?
Is it the newspapers?
是啊 家家都说自我上任以来
Yes. They all say that since my administration came into office
一切都毫无变化
nothing has changed.
您一定特别自豪吧
You must be very proud.
这可不是夸我 伯纳
That's not meant as a compliment.
伦敦总共十份晨报 我全看了一遍
I read all ten of this morning's London papers.
其中九份对我没说半句好话
Not a good word about me in nine of them.
只有第十份好些?
But the tenth is better?
第十份更糟 压根没提我
Worse. It doesn't mention me at all.
今天早晨他们攻击您什么?
What have they got against you this moring?
全都一个口径
They all say the same thing.
说我是个绣花枕头
That I'm a windbag.
老天啊      就是
Good heavens!      Yeah.
真奇怪 不是吗?
Extraordinary, isn't it?
他们说我的执政全是假大空
They say that my administration's all rhetoric.
我说得天花乱坠 可是一事无成
That I talk and talk, but nothing ever gets done.
睁眼说瞎话嘛
It simply isn't true.
各项改革都在酝酿中
There are reforms in the pipeline,
总方针已经今非昔比
a great change of direction.
确立了新的发展观
New schemes of development,
执政理念不断升华
a whole new philosophy of government.
社会结构取得长足进步
Profound change in the social fabric
国家地缘政治面貌也为之一新
and geopolitical climate of this country.
那究竟有什么成就?
So what is actually happening?
眼下还没有嘛
Nothing yet, obviously.
准是汉弗莱爵士      请他进来吧
That'll be Sir Humphrey.      Better send him in.
请汉弗莱爵士进来
Send Sir Humphrey in.
这些批评大概都源自传闻中的
The origin of this criticism is this rumour
金融城(伦敦内城)的丑闻
about a scandal in the City.
你怎么知道?      首相
How did you guess?     Prime Minister.
汉弗莱 我决定回应所有这些
Humphrey, I've decided to respond
对金融城丑闻的批评
to all this criticism about a scandal in the City.
媒体呼吁采取行动
The press is demanding action.
您打算怎么办?
What are you proposing to do?
我要...任命一个人
I shall... appoint... someone.
您什么时候决定的?
When did you take this decision?
今天 看报纸的时候
Today when I read the papers.
您什么时候想到的呢?      今天 看报纸的时候
But when did you first think of it?      Today.
那您花了多久权衡
And for how long did you weigh
这决策的利弊呢?
the pros and cons of this decision?
没多久 我决定要...拿出决心来
Not long. I decided to be decisive.
首相 恕我直言 您未免太在乎
I think you worry too much
那些报纸的说辞了
about what the papers say.
只有公务员才能说得这么轻巧
Only a civil servant could make that remark.
我不能不在乎
I have to worry about them,
政党大会就快召开了
with the party conference coming up.
这流言怎么也平息不了
These rumours of a scandal won't go away.
等它不只是流言再来操心吧
Let's not worry until it's more than a rumour.
请您过目内阁议程
Here's the Cabinet agenda.
先放着 汉弗莱 这件事严重多了
Not now. This is more important.
恕难苟同 首相 关于媒体必须牢记的是
With respect, it is not. Remember, the press
他们只迎合读者的偏见
just pander to their readers' prejudices.
媒体的事我不用你教
Don't tell me about the press.
报纸读者我最熟悉了
I know exactly who reads the papers.
"镜报"的读者是
The "Mirror" is read by people
自以为在治理国家的人
who think they run the country.
"卫报"的读者是
The "Guardian" is read by people
自以为应该治理国家的人
who think they OUGHT to run it.
"泰晤士报"的读者是
The "Times" is read by the people
真的在治理国家的人
who DO run the country.
"每日邮报"的读者是
The "Daily Mail" is read by the wives
治理国家的人的夫人
of the people who run it.
"金融时报"的读者是
The "Financial Times" is read by people
手里攥着国家的人
who OWN the country.
"晨星报"的读者是想把国家
The "Morning Star" is read by people who think
交给别国治理的人
the country should be run by another country
而"每日电讯报"的读者
and the "Daily Telegraph"
觉得我们正被别国治理着
is read by people who think it is.
首相 那"太阳报"的读者呢?
What about the people who read "The Sun"?
"太阳报"的读者不在乎谁治理国家
"Sun" readers don't care who runs the country
只要她前凸后翘就行
as long as she's got big tits.
你怎么看
What do you make of
菲利普-贝伦森银行的事 戴斯蒙?
this Phillips Berenson business, Desmond?
恐怕不妙      比媒体说的还糟?
Not too good.      Worse than the press are saying?
不止是一家投资银行
More than another investment bank
投错了资的问题?
that made the wrong investments?
恐怕是 这才冰山一角呢
'Fraid so. Tip of the iceberg.
具体说说      他们坏了规矩
Tell me more.       They've broken the rules.
内线交易潜规则吗?
The insider trading regulations?
不是      那就好
No.      That's one relief.
这条当然首当其冲 可他们
Of course they've broken those,
还坏了金融城的基本规矩
but they've broken the basic rule of the City.
我都不知道他们还有规矩      就一条
I didn't know there were any.      Just the one.
你要是能力差 就得诚实
If you're incompetent, you have to be honest.
你要想耍花招 就得聪明
If you're crooked, you have to be clever.
如果你诚实 搞出了岔子
If you're honest and make a pig's breakfast of things
大家会拉你一把
chaps help you out.
耍花招呢?
If you're crooked?
有利可图的话 谁也不过问
With good profits, chaps don't ask questions.
他们又不蠢 至少没那么蠢
They're not stupid. Well, not that stupid.
所以理想的公司得既诚实又聪明?
The ideal is a firm which is honest and clever?
对 万一你碰上了
Yes. Let me know if you ever
可要告诉我啊
come across one, won't you?
贝伦森银行呢?      他们嘛...
And Phillips Berenson?      Well, they were...
犯法了      话不能这么说
Breaking the law.      I wouldn't put it like that.
银行董事不是把资本
Were the directors siphoning off funds
抽到自己公司去了吗?
into their own companies?
可能会还回来呢
Might've paid it back later.
不过没还
But didn't.
是暂时没还
Well, they haven't yet.
逃税
Tax fiddles.
他们自有一套办法
They placed their own interpretation
解释财政部规章
on Treasury regulations.
总得有人解释吧
Someone has to interpret them.
财政部出台的解释呢?
What about the Treasury's interpretation?
似乎不大好用吧
It didn't seem appropriate.
资本转移到中欧小国公司去了?
Capital transfers to Liechtenstein companies?
有这么回事
Bit of that.
行贿呢?
Bribery?
外国政府官员私下吃了回扣
Undisclosed commissions to foreign officials.
就是行贿      对
Bribery.      Yes.
您的白兰地      谢谢
Your brandies.      Thank you.
可以买单了吗?      就来 先生
May I have the bill?      Certainly, sir.
那整个内幕什么时候会泄露?
So when's all this going to come out?
问题就在这 不能泄露
That's just it, it mustn't.
你有什么办法?
How do you stop it?
不知道 这就是我说的坏了规矩了
That's what I meant about breaking the rules.
如果利润够高
If they were profitable,
什么也不必泄露
it wouldn't need to come out.
现在他们要破产了 真急人
Now they're going bust, I'm worried.
你有牵涉吗?
Are you involved?
像你们这么大的银行肯定没事吧?
Surely a huge bank like yours isn't affected?
借你吉言 不过我们投了不少 有4亿呢
I wish you were right, but we've supported
你说起来轻巧 汉弗莱
It's all very well for you,
可是当你朝阿拉伯人...
but when you've got all that Arab mon...
当你朝阿拉伯人贷了利率11%的款
When you've got all that Arab money at 11%,
你若不想丢人现眼
you'd look pretty silly
当然要以14%利率栽给别人
if you didn't lend it to somebody for 14.
没几个人能稳出14%
You couldn't trust many people to pay 14.
那当然
Obviously.
于是我们继续追加 让它流动起来
Then we put in more to keep them afloat.
要是你知道他们是骗子...
If you knew they were crooks...
我们不知道
We didn't.
你们可以调查啊
You could've made inquiries.
金融城里没人调查这种事
You don't make such inquiries in the City.
他们看上去挺正派的
They seemed like decent chaps.
正派人不该摸其他正派人的底
Decent chaps don't check up on decent chaps
检查他们究竟正不正派
to see if they're behaving like decent chaps.
糊涂大意值得交4亿学费吗?
And ignorance is worth paying 400 million for?
糊涂是安全保障 上当受骗又不是犯罪
Ignorance is safety. It's not a crime to be deceived
再说也不是我们自己的钱
And it's not our own money.
您的账单 先生      谢谢
Your bill, sir.      Thank you.
那接下来会怎样?
So what's going to happen?
只有一个办法 由英格兰中央银行
Only one answer. The Bank of England
出钱为贝伦森救市
must bail out Phillips Berenson.
不声张 内部解决 大家就都能保本了
No publicity. That way we get our money back.
纳税人买单
At the taxpayers' expense.
当然      能办到吗?
Of course.      Can it be done?
得看中央银行新董事长的意思
Depends on the new Bank of England Governor.
还没任命呢
Hasn't been appointed yet.
是啊 这就是我想谈的问题
That's what I wanted to talk about.
会任命谁?
Who will it be?
暂时没确定 不过据我所知首相
It isn't decided, but I understand from the PM
最中意亚历山大-詹森
that the frontrunner is Alexander Jameson.
不会吧 开什么玩笑      不开玩笑
You're joking? But that's impossible.
你是说他太诚实了
You mean he's too honest.
他还不止是自己诚实
It's not just that he behaves honestly.
那倒没关系
That doesn't matter.
我还有几个朋友也诚实
Some of my best friends behave honestly.
没有耍花招的脑筋嘛
None are smart enough to get away with it.
可詹森也不许别人不诚实
Jameson actually tries to stop dishonesty.
那就完了 事不是这么办的
Fatal. The world doesn't work like that.
是啊 他还写了份可怕的报告
Yes, he did that appalling report
抨击公务员系统浪费资源 效率底下
on waste and inefficiency in the Civil Service.
你得想办法拿掉他
You've got to block him.
不好办 他是财政部推荐的
It's difficult. It's a Treasury recommendation.
可最终得首相任命      对
But the PM makes the appointment.      Yes.
还不止是贝伦森银行的问题
It's not just Phillips Berenson.
一旦詹森开始顺藤摸瓜
Once Jameson starts his detective work,
别的问题也会暴露出来
other things will come out.
金融地震 信用崩溃 货币危机
Collapse of confidence,
英镑会一落千丈
the pound will go through the floor.
对 我明白
Yes, I see.
你得让首相也明白
You must make the PM see it.
信用可不能有闪失 金融城
Confidence mustn't be eroded. The City
每年给国家进帐60亿
earns the country six billion pounds a year.
总不能赌上这些 去追查几个家伙
You can't hazard that just because a few chaps
瞒着股民 私下给朋友帮忙的事吧
do a few favours for friends.
没道理嘛
Wouldn't be right.
嗯...
Well...
多萝西 我很不满意这份
Oh, Dorothy, I'm not happy about
党派大会讲稿 里面没有好消息
my speech for the conference. It contains no good news.
我们想不出好消息
We couldn't think of any.
那就把坏消息往好了说
We'll have to make the bad news look good.
我要讲讲医疗系统
I'll talk about the Health Service.
关爱老人 关爱母婴
Care for the elderly, mothers and children,
向健壮的国家迈进
growing up into a healthy nation.
价廉物美?
Value for money?
这个不能提 人人都知道
I can't say that. Everybody knows
成本已经高得离谱了
that costs are completely out of control.
是哦
Right.
"我们正以前无古人的投资"
We are spending more than ever to make
"打造世界一流的医疗系统"
our health service the best in the world.
很好 再说国防
Good. Now, defence.
我原本想谈削减军费的
I'd hoped to say something about defence cuts,
可我还没说服他们削下一分钱
but I haven't persuaded them to make any yet.
"本届政府不会将国家安全"
This government will not put the security
"置之不顾"
of the nation in jeopardy
"而去追求盲目虚假的节约"
by penny-pinching and... false economies?
就算为了国家安全
Not that we'd put security in jeopardy
也只需要一所音乐学校
by having ONE service music school
而不至于要三所
instead of three separate ones
海陆空三军各一所吧
for the Army, Navy and RAF.
总不至于海军吹起低音管来
There can hardly be a specifically
也和其他人不同吧
Royal Naval method of playing bassoon.
你不会把这写进去吧? 不 抱歉
You won't put that in? No, sorry.
经济方面有利好消息吗?
Anything good we can say about the economy?
经济是个问题 一点利好都没有
That's a problem. No good news at all.
会找出些来的
We'll find something.
会议期间不会爆出什么坏消息吧?
No bad news will break during the conference?
问我干嘛 我只是个政治顾问
Don't ask me! I'm only the political adviser.
您才有权看财政部秘密报告
YOU see the secret Treasury papers.
我在琢磨贝伦森的丑闻
I was thinking about this Phillips Berenson
你作何感想?
scandal. What do you make of it?
大有蹊跷     怎么?
I'm suspicious.       Why?
因为证券交易所主席 劳埃德银行主席
Because of the statements of the chairman
和中央银行的声明
of the Stock Exchange and chairman of Lloyds.
他们没发表声明
There were no statements.
所以才蹊跷嘛
That's why I'm suspicious.
如果传闻只是空穴来风
If there was nothing in these rumours,
他们肯定争着出来撇清
they'd fall over themselves to say so.
真不公平 金融城的丑闻总是
So unfair. Scandals in the City always look bad
给政府抹黑 这跟我有什么关系
for the government. It's nothing to do with me.
有了 我可以宣布
I know! I could announce
为中央银行任命新董事长
the new Governor of the Bank of England.
伯纳 去看看汉弗莱在不在
Bernard, see if you can see Humphrey around.
跟他说我找他 说到哪了?
Tell him I'd like to see him. Where were we?
经济 就业率有起色吗?
The economy. Unemployment coming down?
没有
No.
"我们将把减少失业"
We shall make the attack on unemployment
"当作头等大事来抓" 薪水呢?
our top priority. Pay?
涨得太快了
Rising too fast.
"我们不能再透支了"
We cannot pay ourselves more than we earn.
"世界其它国家没有义务赡养我们"
The world does not owe us a living.
利息率呢?
Interest rates?
太高了      大会前能降息?
Too high.      They might come down?
那就太理想了
That'd be terrific.
我没有那种好运气
I don't have that kind of luck.
如果整个大局都惨不忍睹
If the whole picture's a total disaster,
我们总还可以扯出国旗来吧
we can always wave the Union Jack.
国家民族的伟大使命...
The nation's great destiny...
在世界舞台上的独特位置
Unique role on the world stage.
尽一切可能 建设一个繁荣昌盛的未来
Make every effort to build a prosperous world
造福下一代 下下一代
for our children and our children's children.
大概也只有他们能看到了
That's probably about how long it'll take.
进来
YES?
汉弗莱爵士 首相问您
The PM wonders
能不能在五分钟之内过去
if you could join him in five minutes.
没问题 伯纳 伯纳...
Certainly, Bernard. Bernard...
中央银行的董事任命
Any news about the governorship
有什么新消息吗?
of the Bank of England?
首相正计划
The Prime Minister is planning
任命亚历山大-詹森 清廉先生
to appoint Alexander Jameson. Mr Clean.
这倒是个喜讯
That's one bit of good news.
这是噩耗
Appalling news!
您会劝首相改变主意吗?
Will you try and change the PM's mind?
不
No.
我会改变首相的主意
I WILL change the PM's mind.
他似乎对詹森很有信心
He seems very keen on him.
我知道 这就是我的出发点
That'll be my starting point.
如果你想暗示
When you wish to suggest
某个人不适合某个位置...
that somebody is not the ideal choice...
就要诋毁他?
You rubbish them?
第一步是要表示完全的支持
The first stage is to express absolute support.
为什么
Why?
你不想留下说人坏话的记录吧
You don't want to say somebody's no good.
你得显得像他的朋友
You must be seen to be their friend.
说到底 先得绕到人后面
After all, it is necessary to get behind someone
才能从背后捅刀子
before you can stab them in the back.
可詹森是个好人
But Alexander Jameson is good.
他极其诚实 又有能力
He's honest and efficient.
太好了 这就进入第二步
Excellent. That's the second stage.
你列举他所有的优点
You list his praiseworthy qualities,
尤其是那些让他不称职的
especially those that make him unsuitable.
大肆夸奖它们
You praise them to the point
到矫枉过正的地步 这是第三步
where they become a vice. The third stage.
更好的办法是 你把他的观点扁平化
Or, better still, you over-simplify his views
给它们贴标签 就像你刚说的
by labelling them, as you just did.
清廉先生?      对
You mean Mr Clean?       Yes.
不过我想我们能做得更好
But I think we can do better than that.
坐下吧 伯纳
Do sit down, Bernard.
他不是常去教堂吗?
Isn't he a churchgoer?
对 我记得他做过业余传道士
Yes, I believe he was once a lay preacher.
很久以前了
A long time ago.
太妙了 我们就用这点打击他
Splendid. We can use that against him.
怎么做?
How?
"多好的人啊 有生以来就没树过敌"
Charming man, hasn't an enemy in the world.
"可他真能应付"
But is he really up to dealing with
"金融城里那些恶棍吗?"
some of those rogues in the City?
詹森很强硬的
Jameson's pretty tough.
那就说他强硬过头了
Then we'll say he's too tough.
这是第四步 列出他所有的缺陷
The fourth stage. You name all his bad points
但要以为他开脱的口气
by defending and excusing them.
就像 "哦 有什么关系"
You know - "Oh, it probably doesn't matter
"不就是拒服兵役嘛"
that he was a conscientious objector.
"我肯定...没人当真质疑他不爱国"
"I'm sure... nobody's really questioned his patriotism."
或者 "我觉得大家批评他"
Or "I think the criticisms of him
"搞垮了他上一家公司的事"
for bankrupting his last company
"并不完全公平"
weren't entirely fair."
这么说肯定奏效
That would certainly do it.
如果不奏效 总还可以暗示有别的丑闻
If not, you can always hint at a hidden scandal.
如果他单身 暗示他是同性恋
If he's not married, hint at homosexuality.
如果结婚了呢?      那就通奸
If he is married?      Adultery.
跟一位必须避讳的女士
With a lady's who's beyond reproach.
比如皇室成员之类
One of the royals, for instance.
或者电视女主播
Or a television newsreader.
如果他显然婚姻幸福呢?
What if he's obviously happily married?
说他是个道学先生 或者酗酒
Say he's extremely puritanical or he drinks
或者在接受心理治疗 伯纳你看
or he's having psychiatric treatment.
运用之妙 存乎一心啊 好好学着
The possibilities are endless. Listen and learn.
对...
Yeah...
汉弗莱爵士
Er, Sir Humphrey...
首相
Prime Minister.
汉弗莱 我们在准备我的党派大会讲话
We've been working on my conference speech.
我很担心金融城丑闻的事
I'm worried about this scandal in the City.
我看没那么严重吧 首相
I don't think it's very serious.
当然严重
It certainly is.
不不 亲爱的女士
No, no, no, dear lady.
银行朝一个大客户贷款过度 仅此而已
The bank over-lent to one big borrower, that's all.
有些董事的过去不太干净
Some of its directors have a shady past.
我看没这么简单
There's more to it.
你能证明吗?      不能 是我的直觉
Can you prove it?       No, it's my antennae.
明白了 首相 如今我们
I think, Prime Minister, that we are
已经开始诉诸女性直觉了
in the realm of female intuition.
走着瞧      那就走着瞧
We'll see.      We shall indeed.
至少还有个喜讯 我决定任命
Anyway, the good news is I've decided to appoint
詹森为中央银行董事长
Jameson as Governor of the Bank of England.
那个业余传道士 多好的人啊
Oh, the lay preacher! What a nice chap!
干嘛这么叫他?      他就是
Why do you call him that?       He is.
是吗? 这是好事吧?
Is he? That's good, isn't it?
好得不能再好了
Oh... good is exactly the word.
他真是个大好人 还很出色地主持过
He's a really good man. Did a really good job
白鳕鱼管理局的工作 不是吗?
at the White Fish Authority, too, didn't he?
他在哪传道?
Where does he preach?
不外乎教堂里吧
In church, I imagine.
他这人虔诚得可怕 诚实得不像话
He's frightfully religious and terribly honest.
对谁都绝对诚实
Honest with absolutely everybody.
是吗? 那太好了
Is he? That is good.
当然好 有百利而无一弊
Of course it's good. On the whole.
只要他发现任何地方有丑闻
If he finds a scandal anywhere -
哪怕是10号里的
even here in No.10 -
也一定会昭告天下 绝无二话
he'll tell everybody, no doubt about that.
你是说他不谨慎?
You mean he's indiscreet?
天啊 这个词太贬义了
Oh, dear, that's such a pejorative word.
我宁愿称此为择善固执
I'd prefer to say he's obsessively honest.
好吧 你也觉得他能救金融城吧?
He's the right man to bring the City into line?
还用说...如果您想要个圣人
Oh, absolu... If you want a saint.
当然 也有些人说他
Of course, there are those who say
跟现实世界脱节
he doesn't live in the real world.
他这人极度道学
He is extremely puritanical,
比一般圣经狂都严重
even for a Bible basher.
真的?
Is he?
是啊 都有点原教旨主义的味道了
Oh, yes. A bit of an ayatollah, in fact.
您真打算找位力士参孙
Do you want to risk a Samson who might
摧垮整座大厦 埋葬所有人吗?
bring the whole edifice crashing down?
这倒得提防着点 是吗?
Yeah, that's a worry, isn't it?
对 他对个人毫不尊重
He's no respecter of persons.
尽管有时候冒犯别人
Although treading on toes is sometimes
是迫不得已 他却养成习惯了
a necessity, he makes it a hobby.
他喜欢什么事都开诚布公
He likes everything out in the open.
他对媒体从不避讳
He talks very freely to the press.
老实说 他这人不算...特别现实
In fact, he's not... awfully realistic.
你还知道他别的情况吗?
Do you know anything else about him?
当然 如此的完人难免让人起疑心
Well, one wonders if anybody can be that moral.
我听说...      什么?
I've heard...      Yes?
算了
No.
算了 没事 肯定不会捅出来的
No, nothing. I'm sure it won't come out.
什么?
What?
没事 没事
No, nothing.
我相信绝对没事
I'm sure it's nothing.
财政部常任秘书到了 汉弗莱爵士
Permanent Secretary of the Treasury, sir.
弗兰克 亲爱的朋友
My dear chap.
汉弗莱      快坐
Humphrey.       Sit down.
谢谢 我怎么听到传言说
Thanks. What's this rumour I hear
你在抹黑詹森?
that you're rubbishing Jameson?
那个业余传道士? 我觉得他不错啊
The lay preacher? I think he's a splendid chap.
得了 别跟我来这招 汉弗莱
No. Don't play that game with me, Humphrey.
财政部想让他当董事长
The Treasury wants him to be the new Governor.
为什么?
Why?
因为是时候给中央银行选位
It's time the Governor of the Bank of England
聪明又有能力的董事长了
was intelligent and competent.
这可是创举
It'd be an innovation.
你不觉得值得一试吗?
Don't you think it should be tryed?
可这太危险了
But it's so dangerous.
汉弗莱 金融城的丑闻一桩接一桩
Look, we keep enduring these City scandals.
财政部和部长都受够了
The Chancellor is fed up
整天辩不可辩之理了
with having to defend the indefensible.
对 弗兰克 我明白
Look, Frank, I understand.
你得照顾财政部长的利益
You're looking after the Chancellor's interests.
这是你的职责
That's your job.
我得照顾首相的利益
I'm looking after the Prime Minister's interests
还有国家利益 这是我的职责
and the nation's. That's mine.
汉弗莱 一个诚实的财政部门
An honest financial sector
不可能对国家利益有害
can't damage the national interest.
从长远来讲 可能有益
In the long term, it's a plus.
不幸的是 从短期来讲你也知道
Unfortunately, in the short term, an inquiry
对金融城发起调查会造成信用贬值
into the City would mean a loss of confidence.
英镑会跳水 股价会跳水
The pound would plunge, shares would plunge
政府也会跟着跳水
and the government would plunge.
这个嘛 恐怕就是YP了
Ah, well, I'm afraid that's YP.
YP?
你的问题
Your problem.
实际上 弗兰克 这我可说不准
Actually, Frank... I'm not so sure.
你知道 大约六成
As you know, about 60%
贝伦森银行的呆账坏账
of Phillips Berenson's outstanding loans
都贷给了三家名声欠佳的外国客户
are with three foreigners of dubious repute.
中央银行有责任
The Bank of England is responsible
监督贝伦森银行
for supervising Phillips Berenson.
可他们的监督漏洞百出
That's been a farce.
我知道 调查员全是外行嘛
Their investigators are a bunch of amateurs.
可谁又有责任监督
But who's responsible for supervising
中央银行呢?
the Bank of England?
财政部 不是吗?      没错...
The Treasury, isn't it?      Well, yes...
我怎能告诉财政部长 如果我们清理整顿
How can I tell the Chancellor that if we have a clean-up
责任可能变成他的?
he may be held responsible?
那他就真要辩不可辩之理了
He'd be defending the really indefensible then.
他会需要首相很多支持的
He'd need an awful lot of support from the PM.
对 可他应该能得到吧
Yes, but he'd get it, presumably.
首相也不喜欢辩不可辩之理
The PM isn't keen on defending the indefensible.
会很难说服他的
He'd need a lot of convincing.
财政部长得说 他是受了
The Chancellor would have to tell him that he'd
财政部官员的误导 弗兰克
been let down by his Treasury officials, Frank.
可是...可是...可是...
But... But... But...
你的问题?
YP?
你说得太对了 这真可怕
You're absolutely right, this is frightful.
疏忽大意和玩忽职守之间的
What's the difference between irregularities
分界线究竟在哪?
and malpractices?
证据不足的罪过叫做疏忽大意
Irregularity means it's a crime you can't prove.
证据确凿的罪过就叫玩忽职守
Malpractice means it's a crime you can prove.
还有人看过这个吗?
Anyone else seen this?
没有了
Nobody.
我们怎么会拿到贝伦森银行的
How did we get this secret auditor's report
秘密审计报告?
on Phillips Berenson?
会计师事务所的合伙人跟我有交情
A partner at the accountant's is a friend.
只为了交情?
Just friendship?
他似乎很期待看到
He's looking forward to reading
明年的授勋名单
the New Year's Honours List.
好吧 我们怎么办? 找哪个部门?
All right. How do we do it? Which section?
何不通过威尔士事务部
What about through the Welsh Office
表彰他泄露消息有功?
for services to LEEKS!
我真惊讶巴特莱银行居然
It surprises me that Bartlett's Bank should be
卷入这么深 你不惊讶吗?
so deeply involved. Doesn't it surprise you?
有格雷布克做主席 不稀奇
Not with Sir Desmond Glazebrook as chairman.
他到底怎么当上主席的?
How on earth did he become chairman?
他从没什么新点子
He never has any original ideas,
从来不坚持原则
never takes a stand on principle.
而且他什么都不懂 会附和任何人
As he doesn't understand anything, he agrees with everybody
所以人们都觉得他可靠
and so people think he's sound.
因为这些我才请他来参谋
Is that why I've been invited to consult him
董事长的人选吗?
about this governorship?
他几分钟内就到
He's due in a few minutes.
您大概会发现 他不愿意您
You may find he doesn't want you
任命詹森来做清理整顿
to appoint Jameson to do a clean-up.
有了这个 没选择了
No option after this.
肯定得走漏些风声
Some of it's bound to.
如果上法庭的话
If it gets to court.
由中央银行来援助
A Bank of England rescue
能瞒住最坏的部分
will keep the worst of it quiet.
格雷布克想要我任命谁?
Who will Glazebrook want me to appoint?
戴斯蒙-格雷布克 首相
Desmond Glazebrook.
太对了 伯纳
Absolutely right, Bernard.
关于什么?      你开玩笑吧?
What about?      You're not serious?
掩盖起来的话 谁得利最大?
Who has the most interest in a cover-up?
格雷布克他自己
Sir Desmond Glazebrook.
请他进来
Ask him in.
汉弗莱爵士和他在一起 都请进来
Sir Humphrey's with him. Send them in.
他们都知道这些了吧?
They'll know about this?
对 可他们不必知道您知道
Yes, but they mustn't know that you know.
不然得给那合伙人伯爵头衔了
Or you'll have to make the partner an earl.
戴斯蒙爵士 多谢你大驾光临
Ah, Sir Desmond, how good of you to come.
首相
Prime Minister.
快请坐
Do sit down, won't you?
你们知道 我得任命一位
Now, as you know... I've got to appoint
新的中央银行董事长
a new Governor for the Bank of England.
我想听听你的看法
I'd welcome your views.
对 我也觉得该任命一位
Well, I certainly think you should appoint one.
我觉得首相已经差不多
I think the Prime Minister's
决定要这么做了
more or less decided that.
问题是任命谁
The question is whom.
啊 这可难说了
Ah, that's tricky.
得找个大伙信得过的
Needs to be someone the chaps trust.
我觉得我们要找的人得聪明
I feel we need someone who's intelligent,
有活力 正直
energetic, upright.
呃 等等      你不同意?
Er, well, hold on.      You don't agree?
当然 这主意挺有意思的
Well, of course, it's a jolly interesting idea,
首相
Prime Minister.
可大伙不一定信得过这种家伙
Not sure the chaps would trust that sort of chap.
首相正担心金融丑闻的事
The PM is worried about financial scandals.
你担心金融丑闻吗 戴斯蒙爵士?
Are you worried about financial scandals?
当然 这种事没有最好 可是...
Of course, we don't want any of those, but...
要是你选的是大伙信任的家伙
if you go for the sort of chap the chaps trust,
你自己也不信他这种家伙
you can trust him to be the sort of chap to see
会不让大伙卷进什么丑闻
the chaps don't get involved in any scandals.
他只会掩盖起来      不 一有什么可疑
He'd hush them up.      No, any suspicion,
你马上请那家伙吃个便饭
and you have the chap straight out for lunch.
问问他有没有这回事
Ask him if there's anything in it.
要是他说没有呢?
What if he says no?
信得过的家伙说话 你得信嘛
You have to trust a chap's word.
金融城就是这样
That's how the City works.
你对贝伦森银行了解多少?
What do you know about Phillips Berenson?
What do YOU know about Phillips Berenson?
这个...就是报上披露那些
Well, er, only what I read in the papers.
那就好
Oh, good.
是啊 他们有点麻烦 借了笔小钱给
Yes, well, they lent a bit of money
不该借的人 人非圣贤啊
to the wrong chaps. Could happen to anyone.
你没听到任何传言?
You haven't heard rumours?
传言随时都有
There are always rumours.
关于贿赂? 侵吞?
Of bribery? Embezzlement?
挪用资金? 内线交易?
Misappropriation? Insider dealing?
亲爱的女士 话说重了吧
Dear lady, those are strong words.
你是说都不存在?
So they're not true?
这个嘛...可以用不同...
Well, er, there are different... er...
不同角度来看同一件事
different ways of looking at things.
要用什么奇异角度
What's a different way
来看非法侵吞?
of looking at embezzlement?
要是谁侵吞 你得采取点措施
If a chap embezzles, you have to do something.
严厉警告他一下?
Have a serious word with him?
那当然
Absolutely.
不过通常那家伙只是
Usually it's just a chap
自作主张支了一笔短期的
who's advanced himself a short-term,
非正式 无担保的临时贷款
unauthorised, unsecured temporary loan
朝公司借了点钱
from the company's account
不幸投错了地方
and invested it unluckily.
人有失手 马有失蹄嘛
Horse falls at the first fence, that sort of thing.
那你觉得我该任命谁?
So who do you think I should appoint?
就像我说的 这不好办
Oh, well, as I say, that's not easy.
找不出几个大伙都信得过的人
Not all that many chaps the chaps trust.
这不由我来说
It's not for me to say,
不过如果受到了邀请...
but if one were to be asked...
既然这个人被认为是...
As long as one were thought to be...
当然 人各有志 可是...
Of course, one is committed, but...
如果真是形势所迫...
And if one were to be pressed,
我敢说这个人总能腾出时间来
I dare say one could make oneself available.
就当作是为...
As a duty one owes to...
我想的是亚历山大-詹森
I was thinking of Alexander Jameson.
你觉得呢?
What's your view?
他是个好会计
Well, he's a good accountant.
诚实吗?      对
Honest?      Yes.
精力呢?      恐怕也不错
Energetic?      I'm afraid so.
可你会推荐他吗?      不会
But would you recommend him?      No.
为什么不会?
Why not?
金融城的事很难说的 首相
Well, the City's a funny place, Prime Minister.
一旦你露了馅
If you spill the beans,
开弓可没有回头箭
you open up a whole can of worms.
要是您不想招来苍蝇
How can you let sleeping dogs lie
又怎能去捅马蜂窝?
if you let the cat out of the bag?
要想注入新血 一不小心
Bring in a new broom and, if you're not careful,
可能就得刮骨疗毒顺带割肉
you've thrown the baby out with the bath water.
临阵突然换了将
If you change horses in the middle of the stream,
四面楚歌也怨不得谁
then you're up the creek without a paddle.
于是就吹灯拔蜡了
And then the balloon goes up!
可不是 被他们抓住小辫子了嘛
Obviously. They hit you for six.
等于自摆乌龙
An own goal, in fact.
我还有半小时就要上台了
I'm on in half an hour
讲话里还是没有任何实质内容
and this speech is devoid of content.
我不知道
Oh, I don't know.
你觉得呢 伯纳?
What do you think, Bernard?
我不知道      好吧 我知道
I don't know.      Well, I do know.
观众会起立鼓掌的
It'll get a standing ovation.
鼓多久?
Oh. How long?
三分半钟
Three and a half minutes.
他们都有秒表不成?
Have people got stopwatches
今天就发
Issued them today.
首相 汉弗莱爵士陪同布兰达高级专员
Sir Humphrey's downstairs with the Burandan
在楼下等候 能见见他们吗?
High Commissioner. Could they have a word?
布兰达高级...      他说十万火急
Burandan High...?      He says it's urgent.
怎么...好吧 他最好快点
Oh, all right. He'd better be quick.
不能讲鼓励投资吗?
Can't we talk about getting more investment?
没法鼓励 利息率太高了
Interest rates are too high.
您不能胁迫财政部长胁迫财政部
Can't you lean on the Chancellor to lean on
胁迫中央银行胁迫各银行降息吗?
the Bank of England to lean on the banks?
半小时之内? 一年半载都难
What, in half an hour? Not in a month of Sundays!
中央银行绝对不同意
The Bank would never allow it.
我能做的 只有任命清廉先生当董事长了
All I can do is appoint Mr Clean as Governor.
"哈克拒绝继续姑息"
"Hacker will take no more nonsense
"金融城的丑闻"
from the City."
首相
Prime Minister.
专员先生 真是意外之喜啊
High Commissioner, an unexpected pleasure!
快请进 请坐下
Do come in. Sit down, please.
有什么可以效劳的?
Now, what can I do for you?
首相 高级专员先生
Well, the High Commissioner's
担心的是传闻中
concerned about the rumour
您要任命詹森
that you intend to appoint Jameson
管理中央银行的事
to the Bank of England,
因为他必然会深入调查
which will inevitably create an investigation
贝伦森银行一案
into Phillips Berenson.
抱歉 不过这和布兰达有何关系?
Forgive me, but how does this concern Buranda?
贝伦森这家问题银行
Phillips Berenson is a shady bank
把自己60%的资本贷给了
that lent 60% of its money
三家名声欠佳的外国客户
to three foreigners of doubtful repute.
这三家客户之中两家
Two of those three foreigners
分别是布兰达总统
were the President of Buranda
和布兰达企业集团主席
and the Chairman of the Burandan Corporation.
如果您威胁到这些贷款
If you attack these loans,
布兰达总统就不得不
the President of Buranda will have no option
将此视为
but to interpret this move
敌对和种族主义行径
as a hostile and racist act.
种族主义?      当然
Racist?      Of course.
我无意冒犯贵国总统本身
I've no intention of attacking the President
我只打算...
per se. L-I would merely...
说他名声欠佳
Say that he was someone of dubious repute.
对...不不不
Yes. No, no, no.
我...我...
I... I...
请允许我进一步指出 以种族主义
May I further point out that a racist attack
攻击我国总统
on our President
毫无疑问会令非洲所有其它国家
would undoubtedly create solidarity and support
同仇敌忾起来
from all the other African states.
英联邦国家 首相
Commonwealth countries.
我们会齐心协力 将英国
We would move to have Britain
驱逐出英联邦
expelled from the Commonwealth.
总统首当其冲就得取消
The President would be obliged to cancel
女王陛下下月的国事访问
Her Majesty's state visit next month
布兰达将立刻抛售所有
and Buranda would sell all the British
它购买的英国国债
government stock that it has bought.
英镑会贬值吧?
Would that create a run on the pound?
是啊
Yes.
还有吗?      还不够吗?
Anything else?      Isn't that enough?
专员先生 能否允许我
High Commissioner, will you excuse me
和汉弗莱爵士私下说几句话?
if I have a few words with Sir Humphrey?
太感谢了 多谢您大驾光临
Thank you so much. So good of you to come
不远万里来到我国
and... such a long way.
我会积极考虑您的话的
I'll give your words earnest consideration.
那就好
Please do.
汉弗莱 你竟敢害我落进这步田地
How dare you put me in this position!
不是我 首相 是布兰达
It is not I, but Buranda.
考虑到英联邦传统 您更应该
The Commonwealth club is another reason
三思而后行
you should exercise caution.
布兰达总统是个骗子
The President is a crook!
怎能让他混进英联邦来
He shouldn't be a member of the club.
应该把他赶出去
He should be blackballed.
他们已经出去了
He is already.
对 谢谢 伯纳
Yes, thank you, Bernard.
我真想不通 汉弗莱
I don't understand it, Humphrey.
你玩的什么花招?
What's your game?
你凭什么觉得
Why should I
我会掩盖又一桩丑闻?
allow another cover-up?
你能得什么好处?
What's in it for you?
什么也没有 首相 我向您保证
Nothing, Prime Minister! I assure you,
我毫无任何私人动机
I have no private ulterior motive.
我是在保护您免于自取灭亡
I'm trying to protect you from yourself.
我完全站在您这边
I'm entirely on your side.
我们凭什么相信?
How can we believe that?
因为这次是真的
Because this time it's true!
我是说 这次我尤其站在您这边
I mean, this time I am particularly on your side.
我一定得找些好消息
I've got to say something good
加进今天的讲话里
in my speech today.
要是我不能宣布任命清廉先生
If I can't announce the appointment of Mr Clean
当中央银行董事长...
as Governor...
何不宣布银行降息呢?
Why not announce a cut in interest rates?
别傻了 汉弗莱 我...什么?
Oh, don't be silly, I... What?
何不宣布银行降息
Announce a cut in interest rates
银行不会容忍政治降息的
The Bank couldn't allow a political cut -
尤其是詹森董事长
particularly with Jameson.
格雷布克董事长就可以
It would with Desmond Glazebrook.
如果您任命他为董事长
Now, if you appoint him Governor,
他明早就降低巴特莱银行的利率
he'll cut Bartlett's interest rates in the morning -
您可以一起在讲话里宣布
you can announce both in your speech.
你怎么知道?
How do you know?
他刚告诉我的 他就在这里
He's just told me. He's here.
戴斯蒙格雷布克当董事长?
Desmond Glazebrook as Governor?
可他太蠢了
But he's such a fool.
他满口都是陈词滥调 说起废话
He only talks in cliche. He can talk
能说到海枯石烂
in cliche till the cows come home.
要是降低利率
Won't a cut in interest rates
物价不是会涨吗?
mean that prices will go up?
我不在乎
I don't mind that,
只要我得到通货膨胀...起立鼓掌
as long as I get a standing inflation... ovation.
你不想金融城有个诚实的人?
You don't want an honest man in the City?
格雷布克也不算...不诚实吧?
Glazebrook isn't exactly... dishonest, is he?
不 他太蠢了 搞不清楚
No, he's too stupid to know
自己到底诚不诚实
whether he's honest or not.
政府总不能和金融城搞僵吧?
We can't operate without the City's goodwill,
不能 首相
No, Prime Minister.
也不该无谓地让他们难堪吧?
No point in embarrassing them needlessly.
不该 首相
No, Prime Minister.
多萝西 给我的讲稿加上
Dorothy, fix my speech to include
降息的内容 好吗?
a cut in interest rates.
汉弗莱 请戴斯蒙爵士过来
Humphrey, ask Sir Desmond to come up here.
是 首相
Yes, Prime Minister.
-==www.RagBear.com==- 破烂熊字幕组 欢迎加入